Guide to the Wallace Earle Stegner Papers, 1961-1965
Department of Special Collections
Wallace Earle Stegner Papers,
1961-1965
Special Collections M0184
Stegner, Wallace Earle, 1909-
2.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Wallace Stegner, 1968.
Biography
Wallace Earle Stegner was born in Lake Mills, Iowa, February 18, 1909. A prize winning novelist and author also of articles and short stories, Stegner has been a professor of English at Stanford University since 1945.
Scope and Content
Manuscripts, typescripts, correspondence, printed materials, photographs, and documents relating chiefly to the writing and publication of two works by Stegner, A SHOOTING STAR and THE GATHERING OF ZION. Also includes material on Mormonism used as background for later work.
Container List
- Section I: A Shooting Star.
  - Fragmentary drafts, carbon typescript, 14 pp.; typescript, 20 pp. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - First draft, incomplete, typescript, 333 pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Early drafts and notes. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Semifinal draft (lacks ending), carbon typescript, 488 pp. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Final draft (essentially semifinal draft, with ending), typescript and carbon typescript, 509 pp. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Revisions of final draft, carbon typescript, pp. 309 - 477, 129, 134 - 5, 162, (173 pp.). (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Printer's proof. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Reviews (44). (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence re publication, 1960 - 1961(34). (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, (2). (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Section II: The Gathering Of Zion.
  - Notes. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Early fragmentary drafts, including: (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous typescript and carbon typescript, some with autograph correction, 61 pp.
    - Chapter on 1856 Handcart Migration, carbon typescript, 25 pp.
    - Flight Out Of Egypt, (Mormon migration of 1846-7), typescript, 17 pp.
    - (Same), early draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 24 pp.
    - (Same), as adapted as Chapter 5, typescript and carbon typescript, with autograph corrections, 15 pp.
    - Introduction, two different drafts, typescript, 13 pp. and 16 pp.
    - Camp Of Israel, typescript with autograph corrections, 22 pp.
    - Winter trek of 1847, typescript with autograph corrections, 25 pp.
  - First draft, typescript (partially carbon), pp. 1 - 245. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Late draft, typescript, 323 pp. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Reviews, (14). (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence re publication, 1961 - 1965(65), including letters from: (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Brooks, Juanita, 1961 - 1964(18).
- Section III. Research Material On Mormonism.
  - Bibliographies (7). (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Journals, unidentified, 1856,typescript and two carbon typescript, 10 pp. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Journals, general file, including those of: (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Beebe, Charles E., typescript, 7 pp.
    - Huntington, William, xerox typescript, 28 pp.
    - Pratt, Orson, xerox excerpts from journal as published in The Latter Day Saints' Millenial Star, 1849 - 1850,32 pp.
    - Richards, Willard, chemical copy typescript, 11 pp.
    - Smith, George A., chemical copy typescript, 4 pp.
  - Journal of Joan Rio Baker, from England to the Salt Lake Valley, 1851,xerox copy excerpts from the Logan, Utah, Herald-Journal, c. 1936,58 pp. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Journals of Fanny Beebe. Typescript, June 14, 1857 - February 13, 1861198 pp. (with carbon typescript of first part to April 10, 1858, 107 pp.). (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Beebe family memorabilia, including: (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous, including a leaf picked up July 6, 1865; newspaper clippings (3); Harvard Club memorial to J. Arthur Beebe.
    - Correspondence, with: Frisby, Leah R. TLS N.D.
      - Beebe, Esther, autograph letter signed, 2/22/1877.
      - Cobden-Sanderson, T.G., als, February 2, ----.
      - Dickens, Charles Jr., als, 11/10/1887.
      - Fiske, George L., als, 5/5/1878.
      - Harrison, Robert H., als, 6/17/1884.
      - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, als to Mr. Hammond re: "nor" as correlative of "not, neither", quotes from Shakespeare and Ecclesiastes
      - Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, als and calling card, 6/23/1862.
      - Morgan, Juliet, als, 3/3, 3/17, and 3/20/1866.
    - Invitations, 1824 - 1851(2).
    - Receipts, 1885 - 1906(5).
  - Beebe family photographs, 1863 - 1900(53), including autographed photo of George Peabody, 1869. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous source material, including: (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Frazier, Arthur W., Biography of Thomas Leonard and Thomas E. Frazier, typescript, 22 pp.
    - Guide To the Route Map Of the Mormon Pioneers, published by Millroy and Hayes, xerox copy.
    - Historic Mormon Country, pamphlet. (3).
    - Jenson, Andrew, Day By Day With The Utah Pioneers, 1847,a revision of the account published April 5-July 24, 1897,in the Salt Lake Tribune.
    - Johannsen, Robert W., Overland Migrations West Of the Mississippi, carbon typescript, 92 pp.
    - Map of the Mormon Trail, 1847.
    - New York Daily Tribune, May 28, 1844,article on Life In Nauvoo, xerox copy.
    - Sorenson, Parry D., Nauvoo Times and Seasons, tearsheets.
    - Stegner, Louise, Adventures In Pursuit Of Nebraska History, interview published by the Greater Omaha Historical Society.
    - Wakefield, Eliza M., The Handcart Trail, xerox copy.
- Section IV: Documents.
  - American Association For State and Local History, Award Of Merit, for The Gathering Of Zion, October 15, 1965. (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Secondary source material on Robert Frost (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Books by Wallace Stegner (separately shelved)
  - The Gathering Of Zion, New York, Mc-Graw Hill Book Co., 1964.
  - The Gathering Of Zion,, London, Eyre and Spottiswoode, Ltd., 1966.
  - A Shooting Star, New York, The Viking Press, 1961.
  - A Shooting Star,, New York, Dell Press, 1962(first paperback edition).
  - Una Estrella Fugaz, Barcelona, Plaza & Janés, S.A., 1964(second Spanish edition).
  - Una Estrella Fugaz,, Barcelona, Plaza & Janés, S.A., 1964(first Spanish paper edition)
  - Une Etoile Filante, Paris, Presses de la Cité, 1961(first French edition).
  - Jeder Stern auf seiner Bahn, Bern, Alfred Scherz, 1962.
  - Sabrina, Stockholm, Gebers, 1962.
  - A Shooting Star, London, Heinemann, 1961(hardcover British edition).
  - A Shooting Star,, London, Transworld Publishers, 1962(paperback British edition).